{"tossups": [{"question": "An 8 inch tall statue of Mao Zedong was placed at this site by an expeditionary team led by Wang Fuzhou [[WAHNG FOO-ZHOH]] who used the \"human ladder\" technique to reach it. The 1970 Khumbu Icefall killed various local contractors working to prepare Japanese skier Y\u016bichir\u014d Miura's attempt to ski down this peak. This mountain, also called Sagarmatha, was first summitted by Tenzing Norgay and Sir Edmund Hillary. For ten points, name this Himalayan mountain on the Nepal-China border, the highest point on Earth.", "answer": "Mount <b><u>Everest</u></b> (or <b><u>Chomolungma</u></b>; accept <b><u>Sagarmatha</u></b> before mentioned; accept specific answers like the <b><u>Summit</u></b> of Mount <b><u>Everest</u></b>) )", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Johann Wolfgang D\u00f6bereiner [[DUH-buh-\"rye\"-nuh]] named a set of triads in an early formulation of this display. John Newlands attempted to create this display, which was inspired by the observations of Lothar Meyer. Some members of this diagram were originally prefixed \"eka-,\" and this diagram once contained entries such as coronium and aether. Containing components like hydrogen and helium, for ten points, what diagram, developed by Dmitri Mendeleev [[men-deh-LEY-eff]], organizes the chemical elements?", "answer": "<b><u>Periodic Table</u></b> of Elements", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "At this event, a preacher became famous for saying \"Praise the Lord and pass the ammunition\" to rally the spirit of the troops. This attack, codenamed Operation Z, began after one side exclaimed, \"Tora! Tora! Tora!\" This event resulted in the deaths of over 2,000 servicemen, primarily due to the sinking of both the USS <em>Oklahoma</em> and the USS <em>Arizona</em>. For ten points, name this attack on December 7th, 1941, in which Japan bombed a U.S. naval base in Hawaii.", "answer": "Attack on <b><u>Pearl Harbor</u></b> (accept equivalents mentioning <b><u>Pearl Harbor</u></b>; accept <b><u>Operation Z</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Troops preparing to confront this force were told \"I have the heart and stomach of a king\" by their leader at Tilbury. This force was commanded by the Duke of Medina Sidonia and lost at the Battle of Gravelines [[grahv-LEEN]]. Sir Francis Drake helped defeat this force shortly after he attacked C\u00e1diz to \"singe the beard of\" its nation's ruler, Philip II. For ten points, name this fleet of ships sent by Spain in 1588 in an attempt to conquer England.", "answer": "Spanish <b><u>Armada</u></b> (or Grande y Felic\u00edsima <b><u>Armada</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Great and Most</u></b> <b><u>Fortunate Navy</u></b>; prompt on \"Spanish navy\" before \"naval\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man has been credited with changing how the white U.S. public saw the crime of lynching through his reports on the death of Jesse Washington published in the paper <em>The</em> <em>Crisis</em>. This man, who publicly debated KKK member Lothrap Stoddard, formed the Niagara Movement with his fellow African-American lawyers. The collection <em>The Souls of Black Folk</em> was written by, for ten points, what rival of Booker T. Washington and NAACP founder?", "answer": "W. E. B. <b><u>Du Bois</u></b> [[doo-BOYSS]] (or William Edward Burghardt <b><u>Du Bois</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In Operation Northwoods, the Department of Defense proposed intentionally killing immigrants and blaming it on this nation as a false flag. Freedom fighters used the yacht <em>Granma</em> to sail from Mexico to this nation in the hope of overthrowing Fulgencio Batista. The failure of John F. Kennedy to provide air support doomed the exile-led Bay of Pigs invasion of this nation. The 26th of July Movement led by the Castros took control of, for ten points, what nation?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Cuba</u></b> (or Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>Cuba</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This orator gave the speech \"An Undefended Land\" to preach the dangers of Nazism to the British people. In the poem \"The Rowers,\" this man used the term \"Hun\" as a derogatory name for the citizens of the German Empire. This Orientalist author used the historical \"Great Game\" as the backdrop for his novel <em>Kim</em>. The first English recipient of the Nobel Prize in Literature was, for ten points, what author of <em>The Jungle Book</em>?", "answer": "Rudyard <b><u>Kipling</u></b> (or Joseph Rudyard <b><u>Kipling</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "This man once performed a duet with Condoleezza Rice and the following year performed during a recitation of the names of the dead at Ground Zero on the first anniversary of 9/11. This student of Leonard Rose and Pablo Casals typically plays a 1733 Montagnana [[mon-tan-YAH-nuh]] named \"Petunia,\" though he was also bequeathed the <em>Davidov Stradivarius</em> by Jacqueline du Pr\u00e9. For ten points, name this Chinese-American classical musician, a world-renowned cellist.", "answer": "Yo-Yo <b><u>Ma</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man supposedly diverted an invasion of Britannia to have his army collect seashells along the English Channel. While campaigning with his father, Germanicus, this man earned a nickname related to wearing a child's version of a military outfit. This emperor, who was assassinated by the Praetorian Guard, supposedly tried to make his horse Incitatus [[in-kih-TAH-tuhss]] a Roman consul. For ten points, name this insane successor of Tiberius, whose name translates to \"Little Boot.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Caligula</u></b> (accept <b><u>Gaius</u></b> Caesar Augustus Germanicus; prompt on \"Little Boot(s)\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "While a French colony, this nation's capital of Grand-Bassam was temporarily abandoned after an outbreak of yellow fever in favor of the city of Bingerville. A future president of this nation and leader of the Popular Front, Laurent Gbagbo [[gah-BAHG-boh]], fled in the 1980s due to pressure from F\u00e9lix Houphou\u00ebt-Boigny [[oo-FWEH bwah-NEE]]. For ten points, name this West African nation named for a commodity produced by elephants, now illegal in most nations.", "answer": "<b><u>Ivory Coast</u></b> (accept <b><u>Cote D'Ivoire</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This writer documented a six-week marine expedition in the Sea of Cortez and later went \"In Search of America\" in a rented pickup truck with his poodle. This author of <em>Travels</em> <em>with Charley</em> won a Pulitzer Prize for a novel in which Jim Casy is beaten to death after the Joad family travels to California during the Dust Bowl. For ten points, name this American author known for his Depression-era stories of California, including <em>The Grapes of Wrath</em>.", "answer": "John <b><u>Steinbeck</u></b> (or John Ernst <b><u>Steinbeck</u></b>, Jr.)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "This celebrity served as the public face of the America First Committee, which pressured the government of Franklin D. Roosevelt to remain neutral during the Second World War. This Medal of Honor recipient traveled over 3,000 miles in his personal airplane, <em>The Spirit of St. Louis</em>. For ten points, name this American aviator who did the first non-stop, solo flight across the Atlantic.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Lindbergh</u></b> (or Charles Augustus <b><u>Lindbergh</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One king of these people named Cetshwayo [[ketsh-\"WHY\"-oh]] had his cause taken up by Lady Florence Dixie after spending two years in exile. Following a victory for these people at Isandlwana [[ee-sahn-JWAH-nah]], a contingent of their soldiers were cornered and defeated at Rorke's Drift. The \"horn of the buffalo\" formation was used by a regiment of these people known as the <em>Impi</em>. The conquests of Shaka led to the establishment of an empire of, for ten points, what people in Southern Africa?", "answer": "<b><u>Zulu</u></b> (or ama<b><u>Zulu</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The \"Praises of Italy\" passage is found in a treatise concerning this subject written by Virgil known as the <em>Georgics</em>. Dactylic hexameter is used in another treatise on this subject by Hesiod [[HEH-see-ud]] known as <em>Works and Days</em>, imploring the reader to pray to Demeter. Cato the Elder describes the virtues of animal husbandry and plowing, both subsets of, for ten points, what discipline in his work, <em>De Agricultura</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Farm</u></b>ing (accept <b><u>Agriculture</u></b> before \"de Agricultura\" is mentioned; accept <b><u>husbandry</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "This god is commonly depicted with Ganga [[GUNG-guh]] flowing from his matted hair and with a third eye that he used to destroy the god of love, Kama. This god beheaded his wife's son and guard before giving him the head of an elephant. This father of Kartikeya [[kar-tih-KEH-yah]] and Ganesh [[gah-NESH]] is the husband of Parvati. For ten points, name this Hindu god of destruction, who makes up the Trimurti with Brahma and Vishnu.", "answer": "<b><u>Shiva</u></b> (accept <b><u>Siva</u></b>; <b><u>Shiv</u></b>; or <b><u>Siv</u></b>; accept <b><u>Rudra</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "A Soviet Republic based in this city collapsed after its leader, Eugen Levin\u00e9 [[leh-vee-NEH]], was shot in Stadelheim [[SHTAH-del-hime]] Prison. A conference named for this city resulted in Nazi Germany receiving the Sudetenland from Czechoslovakia. The SA and Adolf Hitler led the \"Beer Hall Putsch\" in this city. For ten points, name this southern German city, which is the capital and largest city of Bavaria.", "answer": "<b><u>Munich</u></b> (accept <b><u>M\u00fcnchen</u></b>; or <b><u>Minga</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One of these groups named <em>Hispana</em> vanishes from history around 120 AD and is known as the \"lost\" one of these groups. Marius made these groups permanent standing bodies and professionalized their subcommanders, the centurions. These groups each consisted of over 5000 infantry members and 120 foreign <em>auxilia</em> cavalry during the height of the Empire, at which time there were as many as thirty of them. For ten points, name these highest-level divisions of the Roman army.", "answer": "Roman <b><u>Legion</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Legio</u></b>; or <b><u>Legiones</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "During a 1781 raid, a force commanded by this man spared the main house at Berkeley Plantation, which he planned to appropriate for his own residence. This man arrived with relief troops to break the siege of Fort Stanwix and joined with Ethan Allen to capture Fort Ticonderoga. This major general later worked with John Andr\u00e9 in an attempt to surrender West Point. For ten points, name this Continental Army officer who defected to the British in 1780.", "answer": "Benedict <b><u>Arnold</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This deity was worshipped in Sparta under an epithet that translates to</u></b> <b><u>\"Willow-Bound.\" This deity, dubbed \"of the Golden Shaft\" was a patron of childbirth</u></b> <b><u>despite her personal (+)</u> chastity. Though this goddess's main cult centers were at Brauron [[BRAW-rahn]] and her birthplace of Delos, a temple dedicated to this deity at Ephesus [[eh-FEH-soos]] was one of the Seven (*) </b>Ancient Wonders of the World. For ten points, name this twin sister of Apollo, the Greek goddess of the hunt.", "answer": "<b><u>Artemis</u></b> (accept <b><u>Diana</u></b> until \"Greek\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This river was originally termed the \"River of Good Omens\" by Vasco da Gama,</u></b> <b><u>though it was quickly re-dubbed the Cuama [[KWAH-muh]]. The Caprivi [[kah-PREE-</u><u>vee]] Strip in (+)</u> Namibia was created to give the German Empire access to this river during the Scramble for Africa. This river was first charted by David Livingstone, who traversed its course to Victoria Falls. (*) </b>Once occupied by the Mutapa [[moo-TAH-pah]] Empire, for ten points, what fourth-longest river in Africa today provides the border between Zambia and Zimbabwe?", "answer": "<b><u>Zambezi</u></b> River (accept <b><u>Cuama</u></b> River before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>The loser of this battle sent his Imperial Guard to capture La Haye Sainte and</u></b> <b><u>Plancenoit [[PLAHN-sen-NWAH]] but was later pushed back by Foot Guards under Sir</u></b> <b><u>Peregrine (+)</u> Maitland. After his Prussians were defeated at the Battle of Ligny [[leen-YEE]], two days before this battle, Gebhard von Bl\u00fccher [[BLOO-kuh]] withdrew north to (*) </b>Wavre [[WAHV]]. For ten points, name this 1815 battle at which the Seventh Coalition led by the Duke of Wellington ensured the final defeat of Napoleon Bonaparte.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Waterloo</u></b> (prompt on the \"Hundred Days\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One group who performed this art form premiered their first piece,</u> </b><em><b><u>Le Pavillon</u></b></em> <em><b><u>d'Armide</u></b></em><b><u> [[luh pah-vee-YOHN dar-MEED]], in Paris in 1909, following it up with</u></b> <em><b><u>Prince Igor</u></b></em><b><u>, both of which were choreographed by Michel Fokine [[mee-SHEL foh-</u><u>KEEN]]. (*)</u> Sergei Diaghilev [[de-AH-guh-lef]] founded an influential Russian company known for this art form, music for which included </b><em><b>The Firebird</b></em><b> and </b><em><b>The Rite </b><b>of Spring</b></em><b> by Igor (*) </b>Stravinsky. For ten points, name this art form of performative dance, practiced by Anna Pavlova and Vaslav Nijinsky.", "answer": "<b><u>Ballet</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ballet</u></b> Russes)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Dance"}, {"question": "<b>Exposure </b> <b>to the </b> <b>chemical Pyridostigmine </b> Round 5  <b>[[\"pie\"-rih-doh-STIG-meen]] </b> <b><u>Bromide led to this war's namesake \"syndrome,\" a debilitating chronic illness</u></b> <b><u>common among U.S. (+)</u> veterans. The end of this war's hostilities have partially been attributed to photos released of the Highway of Death. This month-long war used the codename Desert Storm. The invasion of (*) </b>Kuwait by Iraq triggered, for ten points, what U.S.-led invasion during the George H.W. Bush administration?", "answer": "First Persian <b><u>Gulf</u></b> War (accept <b><u>Gulf</u></b> War Syndrome; accept First <b><u>Iraq</u></b> War before mentioned; accept <b><u>Desert Storm</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One holder of this position advocated for the replacement of the Bonus Act</u></b> <b><u>with the 1965 Highway Beautification Act. Another holder of this position remarked</u></b> <b><u>that \"If you can save just one child, it's worth it\" (+)</u> when explaining her \"Just Say No\" campaign as part of the U.S. War on Drugs. (*) </b>For ten points, name this position held by figures such as Lady Bird Johnson and Nancy Reagan.", "answer": "<b><u>First Lady</u></b> of the United States (or <b><u>FLOTUS</u></b>; prompt on answers describing the wife of the president)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this province, the Solidarity Coalition led by Jack Munro led a general strike</u></b> <b><u>in the early 1980s made up of 100,000 strikers. The Tsimshian [[sihm-SHE-ahn]]</u></b> <b><u>people of this province built totem poles and hosted potlach [[POT-latch]] (+)</u></b> <b>ceremonies. The term \"Fifty-Four Forty or Fight\" concerned the border dispute between the Oregon territory and this modern province. Royal Navy officer George Vancouver names (*) </b>the largest city of, for ten points, what Canadian province?", "answer": "<b><u>British Columbia</u></b> (accept <b><u>BC</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>In an effort to suppress this faith, President \u00c9lie Lescot [[leh-SKOH]] launched</u></b> <b><u>Operation Cleanup in the 1940s. This faith overtook traditional Catholicism in the</u></b> <b><u>early 19th century after Jean-Jacques Dessalines [[deh-sah-LEEN]] declared (*)</u></b> <b>himself head of the state church. Many of this faith's priest caste, known as </b><em><b>houngans </b></em><b>[[HOONG-gahns]], gained power during the reign of Papa Doc Duvalier [[doo-vahl-YEH]]. (*) </b>For ten points name this African diaspora religion originating in Haiti.", "answer": "Haitian <b><u>Vodou</u></b>ism (accept <b><u>Voodoo</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This election year's Republican candidate was the subject of a critical essay by</u></b> <b><u>Richard J. Hofstadter titled \"The Paranoid Style in American Politics.\" A candidate in</u></b> <b><u>this election year used the \"Daisy Girl\" (+)</u> ad to warn that his opponent would lead the U.S. into a nuclear war with the USSR. The modern conservative movement found a candidate in Barry (*) </b>Goldwater, who won several Southern states in, for ten points, which election cycle won by the incumbent Democrat, Lyndon B. Johnson?", "answer": "<b><u>1964</u></b> United States presidential election", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}